Sync & corrections by Elderfel
www.addic7ed.com
- (Men screaming)
- (Horses neighing)
(Horses galloping)
(Swords clashing)
(Men yelling)
아가씨, 저들이
곧 들이닥칠 겁니다
My Lady, they are upon us.
칸이 왔다
사막으로 도망가라
The Khan has come.
Run for the desert.
코카친 아가씨
Lady Kokachin.
아가씨는 핏줄로 보호받으십니다
해치치 못할 겁니다
You're protected by your blood.
They will not harm you.
해치지는 못하겠지
Harm me? No.
대신 쿠빌라이의
할렘으로 데려갈 것이다
Take me into Kublai's harem? Yes.
그게 죽음보다
못하단 말입니까?
Is it not better than death?
그래, 네구이
No, Nerg체i...
칸의 굴레를 쓰고 사느니
영원히 푸른 하늘로 떠나겠다
to live under the yoke of a Khan
is not better than the Eternal Blue.
(Gasps)
코카친 아가씨!
Lady Kokachin!
(Sobbing)
(Theme music playing)
Do we have to attend?
꼭 가야 하는 것인가?
불참하면 눈치챌 겁니다
Your absence would be noted.
쿠툴룬...
Khutulun...
서방에서 오는
씨름하는 창녀 말이지
that wrestling whore from the west.
경멸의 말은 이 방 안에서만
하십시오, 공주님
Please expel any of your contempt within
the confines of these walls, Princess.
왜 오는 건가?
Why is she coming here?
전 모릅니다
그리고 중요하지도 않습니다
I do not know
and it does not matter.
언제나 하는 것처럼
하시면 됩니다
You will conduct yourself
as you always do...
상냥하게 대하십시오
with graciousness.
공주님의 생각보다
공통점이 많을지도 모릅니다
You may have more in common
than you imagine.
그럴 리가
That's doubtful.
(Clicks tongue)
장신구가 하나 더 없어졌습니다
You lost another trinket.
A bracelet.
팔찌 말이군
말을 타고 달리다가
팔에서 빠졌다
It slipped off my wrist as I rode.
채찍을 든 손에 차다니
어리석은 결정이었어
A poor decision
to wear it on my whip hand.
Yes, a poor decision.
그렇군요
어리석은 결정이었습니다
You take great risk to avoid
a greater danger, I understand.
더 큰 위협을 피하려
위험을 무릅쓰는 건 압니다
새해를 축하하기 위해
In celebration
of this New Year...
공주님이 허락하시면
제가 제 검으로...
perhaps you would allow me
to eliminate this danger...
그 위험을 제거하지요
with my sword.
I do not.
그럴 필요 없다
Father.
아버지
출발하기 상서로운 날이구나
차강사르...
An auspicious day for departure.
Tsagaan Sar.
네가 한 일로
우리가 목숨을 구했다
What you did saved our lives.
나도 안다
I know this.
네 숙부도 알지만...
Your uncle knows, too...
그렇다 말하진 않을 거다
but will not confess it.
내가 두려운 건...
I fear...
I will require another New Year
to repay the debt I owe.
내가 빚을 진 걸 갚으려면
한 해가 더 걸릴 것 같다
The Khan will never allow you
back into the Imperial City.
칸께선 더 이상 제국의 도시에
아버지를 들이지 않으실 겁니다
다시 만날 것이다
We will meet again.
(Grunts)
여기서 네 악마와
천년만년 살거라, 조카야
Rot here, nephew...
with your devils.
우린 비단길로
죽으러 간다
We go to the Silk Road to die.
폴로 형제가 금패를
빼앗겼다 하더군
(Byamba) The brothers Polo
have lost their golden tablet.
Yes.
맞습니다
제국 통행증이 철회된 거요
Imperial pass rescinded.
I know.
압니다
묵을 곳도 새 말도
양식도 없을 거고
No lodging, no fresh horses,
no vittles.
- 도적에게도 취약할 것이오
- 비얌바, 나도 압니다
- They are vulnerable now to bandits.
- Byamba, I know.
저들에게 과한 것이 아니오
It's nothing they do not deserve.
(Byamba)
We should go.
갑시다
대칸께서 하얀 달 전에
답을 듣길 바라시니까
The Great Khan will be expecting
an answer before the White Moon.
- 목을 바쳐야 하오
- 진짜 범인의 목을 바쳐야지요
- We must offer him a head.
- We must offer him the right head.
폴로!
(Khutulun)
Polo!
날 맞이하러 왔는가?
감동받았다
Did you come to greet me?
I'm touched.
쿠툴룬이 보고 싶었는가?
Did you miss Khutulun?
The sun felt warmer
on my face this morning.
오늘 아침 햇살이
더욱 따뜻했습니다
이제 그 이유를 알겠군요
Now I know why.
대칸을 알현하러 갈 것이다
I'm to present myself
to the Great Khan.
와서 알현을 보거라
Come, witness the pomp.
We are called to duty, Lady.
저희는 할 일이 있습니다, 아가씨
따라오라
Come.
Escort me or I will
tell the Khan of your disrespect.
날 안내하지 않으면 칸께
그대의 불경을 고할 것이다
Plans been finalized
for the festival?
축제 계획은 모두 정해졌느냐?
그렇습니다
경기가 시작될 것입니다
They have.
The games will commence.
Good.
잘됐구나
Hmm?
왜?
The Latin's mission to Kochkor...
코츠커에서의 라틴인의 임무 말입니다
I sent him. I would like a report.
제가 보냈으니 보고를 받고 싶습니다
뭔갈 찾아 돌아왔습니까?
Did he return with a discovery?
그와 네 형제가
추적으로 알아낸 건
He and your brother
learned as much on their trek
유세프가 암살자의 뼈에서
살을 발라내며 알아낸 것과 다르지 않다
as Yusuf did flaying the skin
off the assassin's bones.
- 그게 전부입니까?
- 그게 전부다
- And that is all?
- That is all.
쿠툴룬이 폐하를 기다립니다
Khutulun awaits your audience.
그래? 전사처럼 입었던가?
여인처럼 입었던가?
Hmm. She dressed as
a warrior or a lady?
전자입니다
The former.
(Kublai laughs)
그 애 참 맘에 든다
I love that girl.
아니, 아니
(Grunts)
No, no, no, no.
- Are you aggrieved, Jingim?
- I am fine, Mother.
- 분한 것이냐, 진금?
- 전 괜찮습니다
Then be fine.
그러면 정말 괜찮아지거라
칸과 제국을 위해서
힘을 내도록 해라
Spirits high for our Khan
and our kingdom.
Let us find resolution
before the White Moon.
하얀 달 연회 전까지
해결방법을 찾도록 하자
I come here, Khagan...
대칸, 저는 이곳에
제 아비인 카라코룸의
카이두의 사절로 왔습니다
as emissary for my father,
Kaidu of Karakorum.
환영한다, 쿠툴룬
일어나라
You are welcome, Khutulun. Rise.
폐하, 누군가 대칸의 사람들을
Sire... we were pained to hear
비겁하게 공격하였다는 소식에
마음이 아팠습니다
of the cowardly assault
on the Great Khan's person.
It is my father's request
and my wish...
제 아비의 요청과
제 바람이라면...
제 기수들과 캄불락에 남아
that I remain with my horsemen
in Cambulac
as protector of the Great Khan.
대칸을 지키고자 합니다
카이두께선 대칸께서
안전하시길 바라십니다
Kaidu seeks to ensure your safety.
제가 모시겠나이다
I'm your servant.
날 지킬 이는 충분하다
(Kublai)
I have ample protection.
But I welcome your presence.
하지만 네가 있는 것은 환영한다
I accept your horse,
your sword, your spirit.
네 말과, 네 병력과
네 기개를 감사히 받으마
You are home.
편히 지내거라
정말 고맙게 생각한다, 아이야
We're deeply honored, my child.
일단 편히 쉬고...
I invite you to rest...
나와 조정의 여인들과
함께 있자꾸나
then join me
and the ladies of the court.
I require no rest, Lady Chabi.
휴식은 필요없습니다, 황후마마
나서시면 따를 것입니다
Lead and I will follow.
(Both laughing)
캄불락을 돌면서
We tour Cambulac
하얀 달 축제의
준비를 지켜볼 것이다
in preparation for
the Festival of the White Moon.
You will accompany us.
너도 함께 가자꾸나
황공... 하옵니다
I am... deeply honored.
잠깐 말씀 나누지요
청공주님
A word with you, Blue Princess.
Why did you not listen to me?
왜 내 말을 듣지 않소?
왜 이곳에서 도망치지 않았소?
Why did you not
run from this place?
왜 밤에 혼자 초원에서
말을 달렸는지 알아야겠습니다
I want to know why you
ride the grasslands alone at night.
누구에게 보석을 남겼는지
왜 남겼는지 알고 싶습니다
I want to know who you
leave the stones for and why.
그대가 상관할 것이 아니오
That is none of your concern.
I cannot protect you
if you do not talk to me.
말을 하지 않으시면
공주님을 보호할 수 없습니다
(Sighs)
마르코, 내가 독사를 넣어놨소
Marco... I planted the serpent.
그대가 그런지 몰랐소
I did not know it was you.
I fear discovery.
누군가 알게 될까 두려웠소
Of what?
무엇을 말입니까?
Tulga... the man you confronted.
툴가, 그대가 만났던
사람 말이오
바야우트 족의 생존자요
He is a survivor of the Bayaut.
- He's your subject?
- Was.
- 공주님의 하인입니까?
- 하인이었소
- 자빙도 압니까?
- 그래서 내가 말타는 것을 허락한 것이오
- Does Za Bing know?
- That is why he allows my rides.
And abdicates his duty.
자신의 책무를 다하지 않았고요
그가 보석을 다루는 건
내가 금하였소
I forbid him from handling the gems.
내 친구를 위험에
빠뜨릴 순 없소
I will not compromise my friend.
I will carry the gems from now on.
지금부터는 내가 맡겠습니다
You wish not to
compromise your friend?
친구가 위험에 빠지지
않길 바랍니까?
Imagine what would happen to him
should you go missing now.
공주께서 사라지면 그에게
무슨 일이 있을 것 같습니까?
(Jingim)
Good New Year to you, brother.
새해 복 많이 받으시게, 형제
황자께서 사생아가 아니라
형제라 부르면 걱정이 됩니다
(Byamba) I worry when you call me
"brother" instead of "bastard."
그러면 꼭 부탁을 하시니까요
- It precedes a request.
- (Jingim chuckles)
난 부탁을 할 필요가 없소
I need not request.
I order.
명령을 하지
I await your command, Jingim Khan.
명령하십시오, 진금 칸
What news from Eagle's Teaching?
독수리의 깨달음에서의
일은 어떻게 됐소?
- (Sighs) None to speak of.
- None...
- 말씀드릴 게 없습니다
- 없는 건가?
말하지 않겠다는 건가?
or none you will speak of?
None.
없습니다
We're talking about my father.
이건 아버님의 일이오
어떤 위험이 닥친 건지
알아야겠소
I will know what danger he faces.
우리 아버님이십니다
(Byamba)
Our father.
위험한 소식은
그분께만 전합니다
I share news of danger
with him alone.
내가 칸께 보고드리면
I disclose to the Khan.
그걸 황자께 알리는 건
칸께서 하실 일입니다
It is for the Khan
to report to the Prince.
그게 일의 순서입니다
That is the order of things.
독수리의 깨달음에서의 일을
알고 싶으면 아버님께 여쭈십시오
You want to know about Eagle's Teaching,
ask Father, brother.
그대가 뭔가 알고 있다면
아버님을 지키는 것은 그대의 일이다
If you know something...
the burden is on you to defend him.
그럴 것입니다
목숨을 다해서요
And I will... with my life.
우리 아버님께 무슨 일이 일어나면
내가 그 목숨을 거두겠다
And if something happens to our father...
I will be the one to take it.
What did Jingim want of you?
진금 황자가 뭘 바랐습니까?
Amends made
before the White Moon.
하얀 달 전에
보상이 치러야 하오
여긴 답은 없고 고통만
있을 뿐입니다, 비얌바
There are no answers here,
Byamba, only pain.
거기에 가장 중요한 답이
있을지도 모르오
The most important answer may lie within.
다음 할 일을 알기 위해선
반드시 확인해야 하오
We must confirm it
to understand our next steps.
(Marco)
Sanga's family has lost everything.
상가의 가족은
모든 걸 잃었습니다
놔요, 놔!
Get... Get...
(Goland speaking Mandarin)
원하면 여기 남으시오
Stay if you wish.
(Boy speaking Mandarin)
(Knocking on door)
- (Boy greeting in Mandarin)
- (Marco speaking Mandarin)
어머니 좀 뵐 수 있겠니?
(Speaking English)
Can I see your mother?
(Spits)
(Goland speaking English)
White devil.
하얀 악마 같으니
울라! 오렴
아이들 데려가라
Urla, come! Take the children.
(Boy speaking Mandarin)
My condolences.
고인의 명복을 빕니다
40일이에요, 라틴인
(Goland)
Forty days, Latin.
애도는 40일간 하죠
Forty days is the mourning period.
Too late.
너무 늦었어요
I was away at war.
전쟁으로 여길 떠나 있었습니다
그것도 좀 된 일이죠, 폴로 공
That was some time ago,
Master Polo.
여기 없었던 더 좋은 이유를
찾아보세요
Find a better reason
for your absence.
(Marco)
I have none.
없습니다
골란드, 상가에게
일어난 일은 유감입니다
Goland, I'm sorry for
what happened to Sanga.
More sorry for
what I'm about to ask.
제가 여쭤볼 일 때문에
더 죄송하게 됐습니다
혹시 상가가 코츠커로
여행을 간 적이 있습니까?
Did Sanga ever travel to Kochkor?
(Goland) Do you suspect a dead man
of another crime?
죽은 사람이 다른 죄를
저질렀다 의심하는 거에요?
다시 살리고 싶기라도
한 건가요, 크리스천?
You wish to resurrect him, Christian?
Crucify him once more?
한 번 더 죽이려고요?
물건을 훔쳤고
벌을 받은 겁니다
(Marco)
He stole and he was punished for it.
I did not sentence him...
제가 선고를 내리거나
죽인 건 아닙니다, 골란드
and I did not kill him, Goland.
내 남편도 스스로 코츠커에
갈 사람은 아니에요
And my husband did not
send himself to Kochkor.
그럼 가긴 한 겁니까?
But he did go?
(Goland)
He collected taxes.
세금 수급원이었어요
Every second fortnight, he rode.
매월 말 2주 동안
여행을 다녔죠
명예를 아는 사람이었어요
My husband was
an honorable man.
남편을 코츠커에 보낸
사람에게 물어보세요
Question the man
who sent Sanga to Kochkor
그런 의심을 가지기 전에요
before you question that.
우릴 놔두세요
Leave us...
제발요
please.
매달 빵 1만 덩이를
나눠준단다
(Chabi) We distribute 100,000
loaves of bread every month...
대칸의 짐승들이 살지면
양젖과 야크 고기를 주지
goat milk and yak meat when
the Great Khan's herds are fat.
백성들이 마마의 은혜를 입으니
행운입니다, 마마
(Khutulun) The people are fortunate
for your grace, My Lady.
백성을 돌보아야...
(Chabi)
We take care of our wards...
아버지로서 칸을
숭배할 것이다
and they revere the Khan
as their father.
오늘 이들이 바치는 존경은
하얀 달 축제를 위해 쉼없이 일하는 것이지
Today, they honor us by working tirelessly
to prepare for the White Moon festivities.
뭔가 잘못된 게 있습니까, 청공주?
Something wrong, Blue Princess?
백성의 헌신과
황실의 후원자에 대한
I was merely observing
the peasants' devotion,
애정의 표시를
보고 있었습니다
their love for their
royal benefactress.
저들의 헌신과 애정에
의문을 가지는 겁니까?
Do you question
their devotion and their love?
아닙니다
I do not.
멈추라
Stop.
Does Lady Kokachin wish to speak
on the topic of the common people?
코카친 공주가 백성들에 대해서
하고 싶은 말이 있는가?
사과드립니다, 마마
명령도 없이 입을 놀렸습니다
I apologize, Empress,
for speaking when not bid to do so.
말하라, 당장
Do so... now.
Has Her Lady walked the villages
of Cambulac without her guard?
마마께서는 호위병 없이
캄불락을 다니신 적이 있습니까?
I have not.
없지
The Empress' perception
of the city is tempered.
황후께서 보시는 도시의 모습은
다듬어진 것입니다
백성이 칸을 사랑하는 것은 고통을
덜어주고 욕망을 채워주기 때문입니다
The people love the Khan because
he eases their pains, fills their wants...
하지만 저들의 고통과 욕망의 원인은
절대 근절되지 않습니다
but the cause of those pains and wants
is never permanently stamped out.
That can breed resentment.
그것으로 분한 마음을
품을 수도 있습니다
그대의 가족이 권력을 잡았다면
이 문제를 달리 풀었겠느냐?
Did you resolve such matters differently
when your family held power...
바야우트 부족의 청공주여?
Blue Princess of Bayaut?
(Breathes deeply)
제 백성과 저의 관계는
다소 직접적이었습니다, 마마
My relations with our people, Lady Chabi,
were somewhat more direct.
Is that so?
그러하냐?
불쾌한 말씀을
드리려는 건 아니었습니다
I mean no offense...
다만 대칸께서 내일
백성의 가운데서 걸으실 때
but the Great Khan should
know the minds of his people
이들의 마음을
알아주셨으면 한 것이었습니다
before he walks
among them tomorrow.
칸께는 내 검과
방패가 있습니다
The Khagan has
my sword and my shield.
그런 마음은 무기로
물리치겠습니다, 마마
I will meet minds
with metal, My Lady.
대칸께선 안전하십니다
The Great Khan is secure.
Is the pain bad today, child?
오늘도 많이 아프냐, 아가?
The child suffers, Chancellor.
아이가 고통스러워하오, 재상
우리도 다 그렇지요
As do we all...
but seeming cruelty
can bring beauty.
하지만 잔인함이
아름다움을 가져옵니다
고통이 평화를
정화하고 이끌어내지요
Pain purifies and leads to peace.
이것이 제가 어릴 적
여동생이 가르쳐준 것입니다
These are lessons my sister
taught me when I was a boy.
The girl is too old for binding.
아이가 전족을 하기엔
나이가 많소
We would have started at an earlier age
were that her father's want.
그 아비가 원하신 일이면
더 어릴 때 했었을 것이오
황제께선 돌아가셨습니다
The Emperor's gone.
제가 이 아이의 숙부고요
I am her uncle.
It is my want.
제가 원하는 것입니다
'Tis a powerful man
who injures little children.
권력을 가졌음에도
어린 아이에게 상처입히는구려
I miss my mother.
어머니가 보고 싶습니다
우리 모두 그렇단다, 해바라기야
We all do, Sunflower...
but I've arranged
to speed her journey.
여행을 서두르게끔
조치를 취해놨다
자, 이제 고개를 돌리거라
Now... look away, child.
- (Ling Ling whimpering)
- (Tightening bandages)
미쳤는가?
Are you mad?
Never contact me.
You will get us both killed.
내게 연락하지 마라
우리 둘 다 죽을 것이다
당장 나가라
Out. Now.
Why are you here?
여기 왜 온 거니?
Jia Sidao took me into the palace...
after you left.
지아 시다오가 네가 떠난 후
날 궁에 들였어
그가 보낸 거야
He sent me.
새 명령이아, 메이린
He has new orders, Mei Lin.
임무를 완수할 때까지
여기 남아 있을 거야
I am to stay until
this mission is complete.
시다오가 이걸 줬어
Sidao offers this.
Tiger root.
호랑이 뿌리야
만지는 건 안전하지만
섭취하면 말도 쓰러뜨릴 정도야
Safe to the touch, but if ingested,
it's enough to fell a horse.
This message says nothing of my daughter.
딸에 대한 이야기는 없어
말해
Speak.
He bound her.
아이의 발을 묶었어
네가 실패하면
더한 일도 할 거야
He will do worse if you fail.
암살을 하라고?
An assassination?
지금 내게 하라는 건
불가능한 일이야
What he asks of me is impossible.
독수리의 깨달음에서
또 무엇을 찾으셨소?
(Ahmad) What else did you find
in Eagle's Teaching...
불순물 섞인 금 말고요
besides impure gold?
상가가 하슈샤신을 고용했단
증거를 찾았습니다
We found evidence that
Sanga hired the Hashshashin.
그가 가고자 한 게 아니라
누가 보낸 거요
He didn't choose to go.
He was sent.
(Marco) We thought you might
offer guidance.
재무상께서 정보를 주실지도
모른다고 생각했습니다
그가 내 밑에 있어서요?
Because he worked for me?
상가는 많은 이들 밑에서 일했소
Sanga worked for many.
From Cambulac to...
캄불락에서...
코츠커까지요
yes, Kochkor.
The Hashshashin
deal in more than death...
하슈샤신은 암살 외에
많은 걸 다루오
black market trade,
silk, coin, salt...
암시장 거래
비단, 동전, 소금...
내가 지지하지 않는
다른 물건도 다루오
and currencies
I do not countenance.
아편, 대마초...
Opium, hashish.
You suspected and did nothing?
의심했는데도 조치를
취하지 않았습니까?
내가 부패를 제거할 수는 없고
증거 없이 죄를 물을 순 없소
I cannot eliminate corruption...
and I will not condemn without proof.
If Sanga were running black market goods
throughout the realm, he'd need agents...
상가가 제국에서 암시장 물건을 팔았다면
그자에게 필요한 건 대리인
군인, 기수...
황실 근위대였을 것이오
soldiers, horsemen... imperial guard.
You have seen my soldiers.
내 군인들을 보셨잖소
주판 앞에서 힘들게
일하고 있소
They toil before the abacus.
그리고 내가 황실 근위대를
통솔하지도 않고요
I certainly do not command
the imperial guard.
그건 유세프 부섭정의 일이오
That's Vice Regent Yusuf's domain.
난 사실만을 말한 것이오
I simply state fact.
Thank you, Ahmad.
고맙소, 아마드
왜 상가를 고발하셨습니까?
Why did you finally report Sanga?
You reported
his transgressions to me.
그대가 그의 죄를
내게 고발하였잖소
Had I not, it would have been
you or I unjustly trampled in the dirt.
그러지 않았으면 그대나 내가
흙바닥에서 구르게 됐을 것이오
소년 황제의 즉위식은
어찌 되어 가고 있습니까?
(Jia Sidao) How do preparations
for the boy's coronation fare?
좌석 배치는
잘 되고 있겠지요?
I trust seating arrangements
are managed?
어색하게 짝을 짓지는 않았지요?
No awkward pairings?
Lord Li cannot tolerate
Prelate Chan.
이 경께선 찬 대사를
못 견뎌하십니다
물러가 주시오
(Empress Dowager)
Leave us, please...
모두들
everyone.
조정에서는 그대를
축출하기로 하였소
The Dynastic Council
has chosen to dismiss you, Sidao.
황제에 대한 충성은
감사하지만...
We appreciate your service
to the Emperor...
이제 물러나주셔야겠소
but it is time for you to step down.
Have you anything to say?
하실 말씀이 있으시오?
You have no authority.
당신은 그럴 권한이 없소
You are an old woman
with a dead husband and no power.
그댄 남편도 힘도 없는
늙은 여인일 뿐이야
You have nothing.
아무것도 없다고!
옹호해주는 사람은 있지
(Empress Dowager)
I have a champion.
홍련회의 팡전을 아시오?
Do you know Fang Zhen
of the Red Lotus Society?
By reputation.
명성만 들었소
농민이라고요
A peasant farmer.
A scholar- warrior
of the highest order...
아주 뛰어난
학자이자 전사이며
송 왕조에 충성하는
영웅이오, 시다오
a Song dynasty loyalist...
a hero, Sidao.
가난하니까요
Because he was poor...
백성일 뿐이지요
a man of the people.
He is not me.
그는 내가 아닙니다
내가 이 소란의 시기에
이 제국과 도시를 인도했소
I shepherded this city, this empire
through a time of tumult...
and that time has not passed.
아직 그 시간은 지나지 않았소
몽골인들은 돌아올 것이오
The Mongols will return.
몽골인들이 돌아오면
그들은 평화조약에 합의할 것이고
If they return,
they will settle terms of peace...
조약은 그와
협상하게 될 것이오
and negotiate
those terms with him.
요새에 온 걸 환영하오
팡전
Welcome... to the fortress...
Fang Zhen.
재상
Chancellor.
Empress...
태후마마
오랫동안 떠나 있었습니다
I have been too long away.
Take your pets
and your porcelain, Sidao...
그대의 애완동물과
도자기를 가지고 가시오, 시다오
and return to the rice paddies.
논으로 돌아가도록 하시오
(Praying in Arabic)
(Knocking on door)
(Speaking English) It is poor form
to disturb a man at prayer.
기도하는 걸 방해하는 건
예의가 아니오
(Byamba) We are here on the orders of
the Khan, Vice Regent... not your God.
우린 당신의 신이 아니라 칸의
명령을 받아 왔습니다, 부섭정
중요한 일인가 보군
A serious matter.
방해한 점은 사과드립니다
칸께서 맡기신 일이라서요
We apologize for the disturbance...
but the Khan has entrusted us.
Do you remember Sanga,
the collector of taxes?
세금 수급원으로 일했던
상가를 기억하십니까?
부섭정님의 명령으로
처형당했지요
He was executed on your orders.
제 아비와 숙부도
비슷한 죄를 저질렀습니다
My father and uncle
committed a similar crime.
They were branded.
낙인이 찍혔지요
My Khan favors you, Marco...
내 칸께선
당신을 총해하시오, 마르코
thus spared your father and uncle.
그래서 그대의 아비와
숙부를 살린 것이오
That was his choice, not mine.
그분의 선택이지
내 선택이 아니오
하지만 칸께선 상가의 운명엔
관여하지 않으셨소
But the Khan had no hand
in Sanga's end.
따라서 처형은 그대가
결정한 사항입니다
Respectfully,
death was your decree.
손바닥에 낙인을 새기거나
손을 자르거나 눈을 뽑아도 됐습니다
You could have branded his palm,
severed his hand, taken an eye.
그대에게도 할 수 있소
I could do these things to you
부섭정의 결정에
의문을 제기한 죄로 말이오
for challenging the dictates
of the Vice Regent.
We think...
저희 생각엔...
We think Sanga was sent
to Eagle's Teaching...
상가가 독수리의 깨달음으로
간 것 같습니다
a proxy for a greater power...
권력자의 대리인으로요
the agent who delivered instructions
for the murder of the Khan.
칸의 암살에 대한 지시를
중개한 것으로 보입니다
상가가 내 대리인이라
의심하는 것이군
And you suspect
Sanga was my proxy?
칸께서 부재하시면
부섭정이 캄불락을 통제하오
In the absence of the Khan,
the Vice Regent would control Cambulac.
쿠랄타이가 다음 대칸을
선출하기 전까진 그렇지
This is true until the Kurultai
elected the next Khan of Khans.
그럼 내게 무슨 동기가 있겠소?
What motive have I, then?
부섭정님, 저희는 죄를 묻는 게 아니라
조언을 구하려는 것입니다
Vice Regent, we do not accuse.
We seek advice.
The Great Lord trusts you.
대칸께선 부섭정을
신뢰하십니다
He does, Master Marco.
그러하시지, 마르코 공
날 신뢰하시는 건
I am trusted...
내게 야망이 없기 때문이오
because I lack ambition.
I desire no... riches...
so I'm incorruptible.
부를 탐하지도 않아서
매수도 할 수 없지
I have no blood claim to the throne,
황가와 혈연도 없으니
내가 물려받을 자리도 없소
so there is nothing
to which I may ascend.
난 오로지 한 가지만 하는
신하일 뿐이오
I am a servant
who has but one function.
Which is?
그것이 무엇입니까?
I speak truth.
진실을 말하는 것이오
It is this respect I show my Khan.
이것이 내가 칸께
존중을 보이는 것이오
내 삶은 그것으로만 돌아가오
My days are driven by this alone.
어떻게 해야 쿠빌라이와
그의 제국을 최고로 섬기는가?
"How do I best serve
Kublai and his kingdom?"
내 섬김에는 명료함이 있소
There is... clarity in service...
but you... lack this.
그대에겐 없는 것이지
그래도 여기
우리가 있습니다
Yet here we are.
그렇지
하지만 칸께서 그대들을 보낸
진정한 목적은 무엇인가?
But with what true purpose...
does the Khan send you?
그대가 어떻게
칸의 신뢰를 얻었는가?
How will you earn his trust?
여길 나가면서
그걸 생각해 보시오
Think on that
as you take your leave.
(Praying in Arabic)
Is my father safe?
아버님께선 안전하시겠소?
왜 내게 물으십니까, 황자님?
아버님께는 여쭈셨고요?
(Ahmad) Why ask me, Jingim?
Did you ask our father?
(Sighs)
I did.
그랬소
비얌바는 믿으시오
He trusts Byamba.
라틴인은 믿으시면서
내겐 아무 말씀도 안 하시오
He trusts the Latin
and offers me silence.
(Ahmad) Whatever they found in Kochkor
was of no consequence.
저들이 코츠커에서 찾은 게
중요한 것이 아니겠지요
하찮은 일로 짐을
지우고 싶지 않으신 겁니다
He doesn't want to
burden you with trivialities.
내게 진실을 말하실 만큼
믿지 않으시오
He doesn't trust me with the truth.
그러면 어떻게 하시려고요?
And what would you
do with it, Jingim?
What would you do
if you had a target for your rage?
황자님께서 분노의 대상이 되면
무엇을 하시겠습니까?
내 몽골인의 심장이
날 인도하게 하겠지
I would let my Mongol heart guide me.
죽일 것이오!
I would kill!
The Great Khan knows this.
대칸께선 그걸
알고 계십니다
황자님께 말하지 않은
진실이 있다면
If there is some truth
to hold from you,
그건 황자님의 마음이
어떤지 알기 때문입니다
he does so because
he knows your heart.
아버님께서 황자님을
보호하게 하십시오
Let your father protect you.
저 또한 황자님을 보호하겠습니다
Let me, your brother, protect you...
until we find a true target.
진짜 목표를 찾을 때까지요
Untrue by an inch.
조금 빗나갔습니다
Untrue by an inch,
untrue by a mile.
조금 빗나가든
훨씬 빗나가든
네 발굽이 모두 땅을 박차는
찰나의 순간에 이뤄져야 한다
It is in the split moment when
all four hooves leave the ground.
숨을 쉬고 시위를 놓아라
Breathe and send.
네가 처음 왔을 때
음은 거의 없고 양이 너무 강했다
When you first arrived,
you had too little yin, too much yang.
지금은 음이 너무 많고
양은 충분하지...
And now, too much yin...
not enough...
Not so simple.
그리 간단하지 않다
Do not strive for the center.
가운데를 맞추려 하지 마라
그저 호흡해라
말과, 그리고 화살과 함께
Just breathe...
with your horse... and your arrow.
(Sighs)
The Khan expects an answer.
칸께선 답을 원하십니다
무슨 답을 드리려느냐?
What answer to give?
그 절름발이 유세프 경은
나무랄 데 없는 이다
The cripple, Yusuf,
is beyond reproach.
유세프는 그의 말 뒤로
몸을 숨깁니다
Yusuf hides behind his words.
그렇게 보고할 것이냐?
Is that what you'll report?
조금 빗나가든...
Untrue by an inch...
많이 빗나가든...
untrue by a mile.
I have no story to tell, Sire.
말씀드릴 것이 없습니다, 폐하
제 친구인 상가가
코츠커로 간 것은 확실하나
I believe my friend, Sanga,
traveled to Kochkor...
누군가의 명령으로 갔다면
그게 누구인지 모르겠습니다
but I do not know
on whose command... if anyone's.
What are your suspicions?
네가 의심하는 자는?
I must say nothing...
아무 것도 말하지 못하겠습니다
혹여 죄없는 이에게
죄를 묻게 될까 두렵습니다
for fear that I may
condemn an innocent.
제가 아는 건 누군가
폐하의 머리를 노린다는 것입니다
All I know...
is someone seeks your head.
(Scoffs)
많은 이들이 그렇다
Many do, Latin.
하지만 내 아이들이
나를 못 본지 오래 되었다
But my children have been
spared sight of me far too long.
이만 나가거라
Take your leave.
Your children want you alive, Sire.
아이들은 폐하가
살아계시길 바랍니다
(Door closes)
Do you still suspect him?
아직 그를 의심하나?
약한 자라면 자신에 대한 의심을
지우려 누구든 고했을 것입니다
A weaker man would surrender a name
to deflect suspicion from himself.
As would a man
burdened with guilt.
죄책감을 짊어진
자도 그렇겠지
I believe him to be neither.
저자는 둘 다
아니라고 생각합니다
우리에게 온 이후로
저 아이는 많이 변했다
The boy has changed greatly
since coming to us.
우리에게 온 게 아닙니다, 폐하
버려진 것이지요
He did not come to us, Sire.
He was left...
그 사실은 기억하셔야 합니다
A fact that bears recall.
(Chuckles)
You suspect the Latin's father?
라틴인의 아버지를 의심하는가?
Did he abandon his son
to serve his purse... or his pope?
그가 아들을 버린 것이
부를 위함일까요, 종교를 위함일까요?
So, what course of action tomorrow?
그래서 내일은 어떻게 할 것인가?
폐하의 호위와 시종들을
구금하여 질문할 것입니다
We have detained and questioned
your guards and staff.
그들은 죄가 없을 것입니다
I believe them innocent.
My suspicion of Marco has waned...
마르코에 대한 제 의심은
사그라들었으나...
지금 당장은 만일을 대비하여
폐하가 믿지 못하는 자는 죽이십시오
but for now, to be safe...
those whom lack your trust... kill.
그 조언을 받아들이면
살아남을 자가 없을 것이다
There would be few left living
if I heed that counsel.
그대는 믿어도 되는가, 유세프?
Should I trust you, Yusuf?
Hmm?
그래
이건 다음에 하시지요
We will play another time.
(Indistinct conversations)
(Byamba grunting)
그대의 유럽인 동무는 어디에 있소?
(Khutulun)
Where's your European playmate?
이곳에 대해
참 무지하지 않소?
He's an innocent
in this world, isn't he?
And you and I are not?
그대와 난 아니오?
No... we are warriors.
아니죠, 우린 전사니까요
이곳에 있어서 남은 순수함도
없어진 것 같아 두렵소
I fear our world strips him
of what innocence still remains.
우리가 그에게
좋은 일을 하는 것이지요
Then we do him a favor.
세상은 약하고 정직한 자에게
너그럽지 않소
The world is not kind to
the weak and the guileless.
씨름 한 판 하시겠소?
Would you like to wrestle me?
신께 감사히도
증인도 없소
There are no witnesses,
save Tengri.
날 이길 수 있다 생각하시오?
Do you think
you can beat me?
I think you wish me to.
그러길 바라는 줄 알았는데?
Not today.
오늘은 아니오
두려운 것이오?
Are you afraid?
I simply hear the blade's song right now.
지금 당장은 칼의 노래가
들리기 때문이오
(Women giggling)
(Kublai growling)
Where you go?
어디 가느냐!
(Kublai growling)
어디 가려고?
Where are you going?
Come.
오너라
칸을 기쁘게 해 드린다면요
If it pleases the Khan.
(Kublai chuckling)
황후를 기쁘게 해드려야지
If it pleases the Queen.
Hmm?
황후는 그것으로 만족하지 않는다
(Whispers)
It does not please the Queen.
(Women sobbing)
차강사르의 복된 날에
안타까운 일이 생겼구나
(Ahmad) Pitiable event
on this blessed day of Tsagaan Sar.
(Inhaling)
It seems life has left her too soon.
너무 이른 나이에
삶을 마감한 듯하다
칸의 후궁은 울지 않는다
The Khan's consorts must not cry.
눈을 흐리고
얼굴을 붉게 만든ㄴ다
It clouds the eyes
and ruddies the complexion.
Death is life.
죽음도 삶이다
Now is not the time for tears.
지금은 눈물을 흘릴 때가 아니다
고향마을로
돌아가실 겁니까, 재상?
(Fang Zhen) Will you return to
your village, Chancellor?
(Jia Sidao) I was too grand for it
when I was part of it.
그곳에서 자라기엔
그릇이 너무 컸습니다
지금은 더 커졌지요
I've grown grander since.
재상이 하신 일을
존경해 왔습니다
I have been an admirer of yours...
from afar... from the battlefield.
먼 곳에서
전장에서요
You have been an annoying thorn in
Kublai's side for many years, Fang Zhen,
수년간 쿠빌라이의 성가신
가시로 일해오셨습니다, 팡전
frightening his tax collectors,
burning his crops,
세금 수급원들을 위협하고
그의 곡식을 불태우고
애국지사들의 정착지에
무기를 공급하여
storing weapons
in loyalist settlements,
그대가 떠나셔도 정착지에서
칸의 만행에
settlements that bear the brunt
of the Khan's brutality
버틸 수 있게 하셨지요
after you've moved on.
나 또한 그대를
오랫동안 존경해 왔습니다
I've long admired you as well.
이제 전쟁은 지쳤습니다
I tire of warfare.
그것이 태후께서 제 자리를
주기 전입니까, 주고 난 후입니까?
Before or after Empress Dowager
offered you my title?
War is pointless.
It never ends.
전쟁은 무의미합니다
절대 끝나지 않지요
Yes... the warrior
who rejects war.
그렇죠, 전쟁을 거부하는
전사에게는 말입니다
태후께선 내 생각보다
더 영리하십니다
Empress is more intelligent
than I suspected.
당신은 더 바보같으시군요
You... more foolish.
We are like- minded, Chancellor...
in our need to defend Xiangyang.
샹양을 지켜야 한다는 점에서
우리 둘의 생각은 같습니다, 재상
I will do so until my final breath.
마지막 숨이 다할 때까지
그럴 것입니다
Peace is possible...
평화는 가능합니다
and it begins, Jia Sidao...
with our peaceful transition.
그리고 이는 일을 평화롭게 위임하는
것에서 시작될 겁니다, 지아 시다오
(Kublai grunts)
Is it time?
시간이 됐느냐?
네, 아버님
It is, Father...
하지만 참가하지
않으셨으면 합니다
but I did not advise
your attendance.
할 수 있는 것은 다 했다, 진금
What can be done
has been done, Jingim.
네 어미처럼 걱정하는구나
You worry like your mother.
유세프 부섭정 또한
제 의견에 동의합니다
Vice Regent Yusuf himself
concurs with me.
Yusuf is worse than your mother.
유세프는 네 어머니보다 더하다
We do not yet know
who conspired against Your Greatness.
아직 폐하를 상대로 누가
음모를 꾸몄는지 모릅니다
소문은 두려움을 낳는다
Rumor breeds fear.
내 백성들은 아직 내 몸의
피가 돌아다니고 있는지
My people do not know if
blood courses through my veins...
아니면 내 몸이 부르칸 칼둔에
칭기스와 함께 뉘였는지 모르고 있다
or if my body rests with Genghis
in Burkhan Khaldun.
I must show them their Khan.
그들의 칸을 보여주어야 한다
약해보이실까
걱정하시는군요
You are concerned
you are seen as weak.
Mmm.
물러가라
I cannot afford to
bolster these perceptions.
그런 인식을
더욱 키울 순 없다
There is no question, Father.
여쭌 것이 아니었습니다, 아버님
You slayed Ariq single- handedly.
아버님께선 아리크 숙부를
단칼에 베셨습니다
Why was that necessary?
그게 왜 필요했겠느냐?
Why did my brother challenge me?
왜 내 동생이 내게 도전하였을까?
He saw me as weak.
날 약하게 봤기 때문이다
Despite what I did...
people still...
내가 한 일이 있어도
백성들은 여전히...
rumor of my decline...
내 죽음의 소문을 퍼뜨리며
and they worry for succession.
후계를 걱정한다
- 후계는 명확합니다
- 하지만 장담할 수 없다, 진금
- The line is clear.
- But not guaranteed, Jingim.
You will be opposed at the Kurultai
when the time comes.
그 때가 되면 쿠랄타이에선
너를 반대할 것이다
Kaidu... Nayan...
카이두, 나얀...
many feel entitled to my throne.
많은 이들이 이 자리의
자격이 있다 여긴다
The throne is mine
and I will ascend to it.
칸의 자리는 제 것이며
제가 이을 것입니다
나도 그것만큼
바라는 것이 없다
There is nothing I desire
more than this.
But you fear I will fail.
제가 실패할까
두려우시군요
칸국에 네 자신을
증명해보여야 한다
You must prove yourself
to the Khanate.
네가 그럴 때까지...
모든 의심을 잠재울 때까지
Until you do...
until you silence all doubters...
I must be strong.
난 강해야만 한다
그래서 오늘
위험을 감수하십니까?
And so today...
you risk yourself?
I fulfill my duty.
내 의무를 다하는 것이다
Rally my people.
내 백성들 사이를 걸어
To inspire your strength.
네 힘을 북돋아주마
Am I such a burden?
제가 그리도 부담인 겁니까?
넌 내 아들이다
You're my son.
(Children laughing)
툴가
Tulga...
I spoke to Kokachin.
코카친과 얘길 했다
I did not come to hurt you.
I came to help you.
해치려 온 게 아니라
도우러 온 것이다
You lie.
거짓말이오
그대가 누구인지 안다
I know who you are.
One of the Bayaut...
a survivor of the massacre.
학살에서 살아남은
바야우트 족이지
I know she protects you.
공주가 그댈 보호하는 건 안다
I protect her.
내가 공주를 보호하오
No more.
더 이상은 아니다
If I found you,
someone else will find you.
내가 그댈 찾았으니
다른 누군가도 찾을 것이다
It will be your undoing and hers.
그러면 그대도 공주도 끝이다
You risk the Princess.
공주를 위험에 빠뜨리는 것이다
내겐 공주님이 전부요
The Princess is all I have.
공주님을 사랑하는군
You love her.
정혼을 했소
아주 오래 전에
There was an arrangement... long ago.
우린 맺어질 인연이오
We are to be together.
I will bring you the stones.
You will not see Kokachin.
내가 보석을 가져오겠다
다시는 코카친을 볼 수 없다
But you will live.
하지만 목숨은 부지할 것이다
- (Drumming)
- (Villagers chanting)
모두 절로써
그대의 주군을 숭배하라
(Jingim) All bow down
and worship at once your Lord.
God save and keep our Lord long
with joy and gladness.
신께서 우리의 주군께
장수와 기쁨을 드릴지니
Long live the Khan of Khans!
칸 중의 칸이시여 영원하라!
(Drumroll)
울라
Urla.
하얀 달의 밤에는
줄을 서 있지 않아요
No line up for water
on the night of the White Moon.
I'm sorry for what happened
to your father.
네 아버지 일은 유감이다
As you said,
you did not sentence him...
공의 말씀대로
공이 형을 내리지 않았고
아버지가 도둑이었다면
벌을 받아 마땅했습니다
and if he was a thief,
he was deserving of punishment.
상가는 좋은 사람이었다
Sanga was a good man.
아버지께서 무슨 짓을 하셨을까요?
What do you think he did?
What was it Ahmad sent him to do?
아마드 재무상이
무엇을 하라 보낸 것일까요?
I cannot answer that.
그에는 답할 수 없다
Never again breathe that suspicion.
그 의심은 다시는
입밖에 내지 말아라
For your family's sake... never.
네 가족을 위해서
절대 하지 말아라
Move on.
잊거라
Help your family
to find a future without him.
네 가족의 미래를 위해
쓰도록 해라
(Rhythmic drumming)
팔찌는 전달했습니다
The bracelet is delivered.
I am most grateful.
정말 고맙소
이 신세는 후에 갚겠소
I will repay your gesture
in the future.
You can repay it now...
with the answer to a question.
지금 갚으셔도 됩니다
제 질문에 답하시는 걸로요
어떻게 평민이
공주와 혼인을 합니까?
How is it that a peasant
weds a princess?
No royal marries
beneath their station.
왕족은 신분이 낮은 자와
혼인할 수 없소
Then Tulga is delusional?
그럼 툴가가
미친 것입니까?
I could not be with Tulga, Master Marco,
any more than I could be with you.
난 툴가와 함께 할 수 없소, 마르코 공
당신과도 마찬가지요
제 질문에 대한 답을
피하십니다, 청공주
You avoid a direct answer
to my question, Blue Princess.
Silence is no shield, Kokachin.
침묵은 당신을
지킬 수 없습니다, 코카친
제가 그대의 하인에게
보석을 전달하길 바라시면
If you expect me to deliver
the gems to your subject,
그자가 미친 자인지
알아야겠습니다
I need to know
if that subject is mad.
아니오
He is not.
그러면 혼인을 하여야겠군요
Then there are nuptials
to be arranged.
칸께서는 아십니까?
Is the Khan aware?
그대의 말이 웃기지 않소
You lack humor, Latin.
I intend none.
그럴 의도 전혀 없습니다
I am deceived.
제가 속은 것이지요
It is time for Jingim
to take a new wife, I think.
진금이 새 아내를
맞을 때가 된 듯합니다
아이를 잘 낳을
계집이길 바라오
A more fertile bitch, I hope.
다른 것들은
고비 사막처럼 메말랐어
- The rest are barren as my Gobi.
- (Chuckles)
I trust you have
someone in mind?
맘에 두고 있는 후보가 있겠지?
(People cheering)
멈춰라!
Stop!
(People exclaiming)
(Choking)
(People screaming)
(Soldier grunting)
(Gasping)
(Soldiers shouting)
(Grunts)
(Wailing)
Sync & corrections by Elderfel
www.addic7ed.com